VITHIKA RAHUL

20

Nil 5 FIRST FLOOR MALVIYA NAGAR NEW
DELHI
9871057666
vithikarahul@gmail.com

OBJECTIVE

My outstanding academic preparation and excellent organizational skills aid in my ability to be a successful mentor. I possess strong leadership and communication skills that help me to interact well with school faculty, parents and other key educational stakeholders.

I am an empathic listener and dedicated to nurture the potential of children by creating a positive learning environment for my students.

EDUCATION

Sno	Examination	Year	University	% of marks	Regular/ Distance Educatio n Mode
1.	X	1992	Maharaja Sawai Man Singh	71	Regular
2.	XII	1994	Maharaja Sawai Man Singh	75.8	Regular
3.	B.A	1997	Maharani' s College	I Div	Regular
4.	M.A	1999	Rajasthan university	I Div	Regular
	B.Ed.	2008	IGNOU	I Div	Distance
	PG diploma in guidance and counselling, NCERT	2000	NCERT	I Div	Regular

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCES

1. 2001-2003

Taught Psychology in Amity International School, Saket

2. 2003-2007

Worked as school counsellor as well as psychology teacher in Birla Vidya Niketan, Pusha Vihar

3. 2007-Present

I worked as HOD Psychology at DPS R.K Puram from 2007-2018.

Presently working as senior most faculty Psychology in DPS R K Puram

PROFESSIONAL SKILS

- Excellent Knowledge Of Psychology With Expertise In Personal And Career Counselling
- Empathic listening and communication skills, helping me to build rapport with parents, students and staff members.
- Critical thinking and complex problem-solving skills helping me to take appropriate, fair and wise decisions.
- Set up psychology departments in schools like Amity International and Birla Vidya Niketan

SKILLS & ABILITIES

I started psychology club in DPS R K Puram that organizes various activities ranging from Power point presentation to quizzes, essay writing, poster making, and panel discussions etc. for students.
Frequent Teacher training workshop s have been conducted under my supervision to introduce innovative methodologies in teaching.
Workshops like dance therapy and creative art therapy have been organized for students for enhancement of their knowledge and interest in the subject.
I have organized anti-bullying workshop was for class VI at DPS RK Puram.
For increasing student's participation ANNUAL EXHIBITION for psychology have been organized.
MOSAIC the annual psycho socio fest was started in 2010. It is organized every year with full zest and enthusiasm where more than 40 schools participate.
Psyche-Express the annual psychology magazine provides a forum for students to discuss various issues and opinions.
I have done my Guidance and Counseling Course from NCERT in 2000. This is a very prestigious course with limited seats for which an all India level examination was conducted followed by an interview.
I am a part of CBSE examination helpline that helps students to deal with stress especially during examination. Since 2004 I have been helping students to cope up with stress. For this I have also been called as subject expert by various news channels like LOK SABHA channel, DD National, Mirror Now.
As an expert I have been giving my advice during examination to different newspapers.
Along with teaching students I have been a responsible citizen by raising my voice against some sensitive issues

such ads from being published in the newspaper.
While doing my post-graduation I was helping children suffering from Cerebral Palsy with profound retardation at Disha in Jaipur.
I am also registered in the Directory of guidance and counseling Personnel prepared by NCERT.
Involve in Psychological and Behavioral counseling of classes XI and XII

such as obscene advertisement and I have tried to prevent

SEMINARS AND CONEFRENCES

- Presented paper on 'positive teaching to nurture creativity among children' at 4th International conference on Psychology and Allied Sciences at Goa in 2016.
- Attended Counselling skill enrichment programme conducted by NCERT, Delhi. I was the only participant invited from Delhi.
- I have been invited as a panelist for the "National Launch Ceremony of "School Cyber Security Program" held at Ansal University.
- Organized talk on "Identifying Clinical Problems in School children and their Management". The talk was delivered by experts Dr. Sameer Guliani and Ms. Aditi Kaul.
- Organized a 6 days counseling workshop for training in guidance and Counselling with Indian Association of Health, Research and Welfare.
- Panelist on bullying behavior exhibited in schools organized by VIMHANS at Indian Habitat center.
- Conducted sessions with Parents and students on Importance of Career planning at Ramjas School R K Puram.
- Conducted workshop on using Multiple Intelligence theory in classrooms.
- Conducted sessions Counselor training session with Etasha

- Awarded for my services in the field of Guidance and Counselling with Global Education Promotion Council on 24/11/2018
- Part of counselor's team MANODARPAN project started by MHRD for psychosocial support for mental health and wellbeing

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Being in the field of education for almost 19 years I have been actively contributing my services to this field. I am also modifying and growing as a learner as I strongly believe that that education is about unlearning and learning.